AD.MC.012
AbuDhabi
Engin Ozendes Collection
Bulk, 1890-1920
1900-1920
AD.MC.012
AbuDhabi
5.0 Paige boxes
Scope and Contents note
The Engin Ozendes collection includes 315 iconic photographs taken by some of the most prominent photographers and photography studios who documented the last days of the Ottoman Empire and the early Republic period, including Abdullah Freres, Basile Kargapoulo, Zangaki, Sebah & Joaillier, Pascal Sebah, Derounian Freres, Othmar Pferschy, M. Iranian, Berggren, and Arif Hikmet Koyunoglu. The majority of the photographs, all of which are prints, date from the 1890s to 1910s.
The collection’s studio photographs, from various places within the boundaries of modern-day Turkey, Syria, Iraq, Lebanon, Egypt, Greece, Palestine and Israel, present people as everything from simply children and parents, brides and grooms, to prominent military, religious and political figures. Historically significant moments related to both cultural events and military campaigns are represented as well as candid views of street life in cities and towns. The collection depicts the art and architecture from mosques and other religious and archaeological sites from throughout the region, revealing details that in some cases no longer exist, or exist in a different form today.
Arrangement note
The collection was processed as it was received.
Conditions Governing Access note
Digitization of this collection was completed in April 2016.
Custodial History note
Akkasah, the Center for Photography at NYU Abu Dhabi, acquired the collection in December 2015.
Biographical/Historical note
Engin Ozendes began researching the history of Turkish photography in 1974. Her articles on this subject have been published in numerous newspapers, magazines and encyclopedias. She has served as a jury member for many photographic competitions, and delivered lectures. In 1990 she was awarded the title Excellence Fiap (ESFIAP) by the Federation Internationale de L’Art Photographique (FIAP) for her services to photography. Between June 2004 - May 2011 she worked as Curator of Photography Exhibitions at Istanbul Museum of Modern Art. She curated many photography exhibitions internationally. Her books include Photography in the Ottoman Empire 1839-1919 (Haset Publications, 1987), Photography in the Ottoman Empire 1839-1919 (Iletisim, 1995), Abdullah Freres: Ottoman Court Photographers (Yapi Kredi. 1998), From Sebah & Joaillier to Foto Sabah: Orientalism in Photography (Yapi Kredi, 1999), Photography in Turkey (Tarih Vakfi, 1999), Merhaba Atina Here Istanbul (Tarih Vakfi, 2000), Photography in the Ottoman Empire 1839-1923 (Yapi Endustri, 2013), Modern and Contemporary Approaches to Photography in Turkey (Yapi Endustri, 2016).
Computers
- Boy in a dark jacket, leaning on a carved wood banister. 10.6 x 6.7 cm, 1889; Sebah & Joaillier, Pera, Constantinople (Box 1, Folder 1)
  Albumen Prints; Boys; Constantinople; Furnishings; Individual Portraits; Istanbul, Turkey; Painted Backdrops; Photographic Prints; Studio Photography
- Man with a mustache and beard in a three piece suit with a hat and a pin below his collar. Same man from ref3. 10.7 x 6.3 cm, 1888; Studio F. Stoklas, Baden, Germany (Box 1, Folder 1)
  Albumen Prints; Baden, Germany; Fezes / Tarbouches; Hats; Individual Portraits; Men; Photographic Prints; Studio Photography; Suits
- Man in a three piece, wearing a fez and a pin below the center of his collar. 10.7 X 6.4 cm, 1888; Studio F. Stoklas, Baden, Germany (Box 1, Folder 1)
  Albumen Prints; Baden, Germany; Fezes / Tarbouches; Men; Photographic Prints; Studio Photography; Suits
- Seroupe Takvoryan in a three piece suit with a striped tie. 10.4 x 6.4 cm, Undated; Studio Fr. Marutzky, Neuchatel, Switzerland (Box 1, Folder 1)
  Albumen Prints; Fezes / Tarbouches; French Writing; Individual Portraits; Men; Neuchatel, Switzerland; Photographic Prints; Studio Photography; Suits
- Tahsin, holding sword. 10.8 x 6.8 cm, 21 Aralık 1909; Unknown (Box 1, Folder 1)
  Albumen Prints; Men; Military / Soldiers; Ottoman Writing; Photographic Prints; Studio Photography; Swords & Knives; Turkey; Uniforms
- Mehmet Pasha. 10.4 x 6.4 cm, 29 Temmuz 1913; Unknown (Box 1, Folder 1)
  Albumen Prints; Hats; Men; Mustaches; Ottoman Writing; Photographic Prints; Studio Photography; Turkey; Uniforms
- Woman in dress with her right hand resting on a wooden pedestal. 10.9 x 6.9 cm, June 1892; Sebah & Joaillier, Pera, Constantinople (Box 1, Folder 1)
  Albumen Prints; Armenian Writing; Constantinople; Furnishings; Individual Portraits; Istanbul, Turkey; Painted Backdrops; Photographic Prints; Studio Photography; Women
- Therese Honegger as baby girl, sitting on a chair. Subject also in ref51 and ref69. 10.5 x 6.3 cm., 1860s; Abdullah Freres, Constantinople (Box 1, Folder 1)
  Albumen Prints; Children; Constantinople; Furnishings; Girls; Istanbul, Turkey; Photographic Prints; Studio Photography
- Portrait of Sinasi Sadun on a motorcycle. Ottoman writing in blue in on front, Ottoman writing in pencil on back. 6.8 x 9.3 cm, 30 March 1924; Unknown (Box 1, Folder 1)
  Albumen Prints; Hats; Men; Motorcycles; Ottoman Writing; Photographic Prints; Turkey
- Two bell ringers at the Surp Kevork Armenian church in Samatya, Istanbul. 12.2 x 8.1 cm, Undated; Unknown (Box 1, Folder 1)
  Albumen Prints; Coats; Hats; Istanbul, Turkey; Men; Photographic Prints; Studio Photography; Turkish Writing
- Second Lieutenant Nuri. Presented to Seyit Habibullah Efendi in mark of his affection. 18 x 10.8 cm, 13 October 1913; Sakib, Ali; Studio Fotografhane-i Osmani ve Aflam, Besiktas, Istanbul, Turkey (Box 1, Folder 3)
  Albumen Prints; Boots; Constantinople; Hats; Individual Portraits; Istanbul, Turkey; Military / Soldiers; Ottoman Writing; Painted Backdrops; Photographic Prints; Skopje, Macedonia; Studio Photography; Swords & Knives; Uniforms
- Haldun, aged 2, in white outfit. 16.5 x 10.6 cm, 7 June 1895; Studio Photographie Moriglioni, Bursa, Turkey (Box 1, Folder 2)
  Albumen Prints; Boys; Bursa, Turkey; Children; French Writing; Furnishings; Greek Writing; Ottoman Writing; Painted Backdrops; Photographic Prints; Studio Photography
- Haldun, aged 2, in dark outfit standing. 16.5 x 10.6 cm, 7 November 1894; Studio Photographie Moriglioni, Bursa, Turkey (Box 1, Folder 2)
  Albumen Prints; Boys; Children; Individual Portraits; Ottoman Writing; Photographic Prints; Studio Photography; Turkey
- Haldun in garment with belt. "To my dear Aunt Vangeli." 16.2 x 10.7 cm, 7 February 1901; Studio Photographie Moriglioni, Bursa, Turkey (Box 1, Folder 2)
  Albumen Prints; Carpets; Children; Furnishings; Individual Portraits; Ottoman Writing; Photographic Prints; Potted Plants; Studio Photography; Turkey
- Haldun, in garment with belt. "To my dear grandmother and my uncles". 16.2 x 10.7 cm, 7 February 1901; Studio Photographie Moriglioni, Bursa, Turkey (Box 1, Folder 3)
- Woman in dress with embroidery. 16.5 x 10.5 cm, 7 January 1903; Unknown (Box 1, Folder 3)
  Albumen Prints; Embroidery; Individual Portraits; Jewellery; Ottoman Writing; Photographic Prints; Studio Photography; Turkey; Women
- Portrait of Sadun in dark jacket with belt. 16.4 x 10.4 cm, 24 December 1902; Unknown (Box 1, Folder 3)
  Albumen Prints; Boys; Children; Coats; Fezes / Tarbouches; Gloves; Hats; Individual Portraits; Ottoman Writing; Painted Backdrops; Photographic Prints; Studio Photography; Turkey
- Sema Sarim (?) in a print dress. 16.4 x 10.4 cm, 24 December 1902; Unknown (Box 1, Folder 4)
  Albumen Prints; Children; Constantinople; Individual Portraits; Istanbul, Turkey; Ottoman Writing; Photographic Prints; Studio Photography
- Portrait of Hasnun Galib in a light outfit, wearing a fez. 16.5 x 10.5 cm, 13 December 1902; Unknown (Box 1, Folder 4)
  Albumen Prints; Boys; Fezes / Tarbouches; Flowers; Furnishings; Hats; Individual Portraits; Istanbul, Turkey; Ottoman Writing; Painted Backdrops; Photographic Prints; Studio Photography
- Portrait of a soldier, holding rifle with bayonet. 18.2 x 12.5 cm, Unknown; Studio Fotografhane-i Osmani ve Aflam, Besiktas, Istanbul, Turkey (Box 1, Folder 4)
  Albumen Prints; Fezes / Tarbouches; Furnishings; Guns; Individual Portraits; Istanbul, Turkey; Men; Military / Soldiers; Painted Backdrops; Photographic Prints; Studio Photography; Turkish Writing; Uniforms
- Woman in light-colored dress. 16.6 x 10.7 cm, 1903; Sebah & Joaillier, Pera, Constantinople (Box 1, Folder 5)
  Albumen Prints; Constantinople; Individual Portraits; Istanbul, Turkey; Photographic Prints; Studio Photography; Women
- Woman with long hair standing in dark dress with buckled leather straps on her wrists. 16.2 x 10.1 cm, 1889; Sebah & Joaillier, Pera, Constantinople (Box 1, Folder 5)
  Albumen Prints; Constantinople; Furnishings; Individual Portraits; Istanbul, Turkey; Painted Backdrops; Photographic Prints; Studio Photography; Women
- Man with mustache wearing a three piece suit and a fez. 16.2 x 10.6 cm, 1889; Sebah & Joaillier, Pera, Constantinople (Box 1, Folder 5)
  Albumen Prints; Constantinople; Fezes / Tarbouches; Hats; Individual Portraits; Istanbul, Turkey; Men; Mustaches; Photographic Prints; Studio Photography
- Man in long coat holding a cane and hat. 16.3 x 10.4 cm, 1889; Sebah & Joaillier, Pera, Constantinople (Box 1, Folder 6)
  Albumen Prints; Canes & Walking Sticks; Constantinople; Furnishings; Gloves; Hats; Individual Portraits; Istanbul, Turkey; Jewellery; Men; Mustaches; Painted Backdrops; Photographic Prints; Studio Photography
- Girl in white dress with lace trim and a white bow in her hair. 16.4 x 10.8 cm, Undated; Sebah & Joaillier, Pera, Constantinople (Box 1, Folder 6)
  Albumen Prints; Children; Constantinople; Girls; Individual Portraits; Istanbul, Turkey; Photographic Prints; Studio Photography
- Woman in dark dress with lace trim. 16.5 x 10.7 cm, 1888; Sebah & Joaillier, Pera, Constantinople (Box 1, Folder 6)
  Albumen Prints; Constantinople; Furnishings; Individual Portraits; Istanbul, Turkey; Photographic Prints; Studio Photography; Women
- Man in dark coat with a flower in his lapel. 16.4 x 10.6 cm, Undated; Sebah & Joaillier, Pera, Constantinople (Box 1, Folder 7)
  Albumen Prints; Constantinople; Flowers; Individual Portraits; Istanbul, Turkey; Men; Mustaches; Photographic Prints; Studio Photography
- Man with mustache in suit with white bow tie and military medal on lapel. 16.5 x 10.5 cm, 11 November 1900; Sebah & Joaillier, Pera, Constantinople (Box 1, Folder 7)
  Albumen Prints; Books; Bow Ties; Constantinople; Furnishings; German Writing; Gloves; Individual Portraits; Istanbul, Turkey; Jewellery; Men; Mustaches; Photographic Prints; Studio Photography
- Family portrait of a couple and their baby in a lace gown. 16.6 x 10.6 cm, April 1901; Sebah & Joaillier, Pera, Constantinople (Box 1, Folder 7)
  Albumen Prints; Bow Ties; Children; Constantinople; Embroidery; English Writing; Family; Family Portraits; Furnishings; Istanbul, Turkey; Men; Photographic Prints; Studio Photography; Women
- Three brothers and their sister. Same children as ref31. 16.7 x 10.7 cm, 1901; Sebah & Joaillier, Pera, Constantinople (Box 1, Folder 8)
  Albumen Prints; Boys; Children; Constantinople; Family; Family Portraits; Fezes / Tarbouches; Furnishings; Girls; Group Portraits; Hats; Istanbul, Turkey; Painted Backdrops; Photographic Prints; Studio Photography
- Three brothers and their sister, standing in a row. 16.4 x 10.8 cm, 1900; Sebah & Joaillier, Pera, Constantinople (Box 1, Folder 8)
  Albumen Prints; Boys; Children; Constantinople; Family; Family Portraits; Furnishings; Girls; Istanbul, Turkey; Painted Backdrops; Photographic Prints; Potted Plants; Studio Photography
- Meur. & Mme Meissner Pacha and their daughter, Lucette. 16.5 x 10.5 cm, 1901; Sebah & Joaillier, Pera, Constantinople (Box 1, Folder 8)
  Albumen Prints; Beards; Children; Constantinople; Eye Glasses & Sunglasses; Family; Family Portraits; Furnishings; Girls; Group Portraits; Istanbul, Turkey; Men; Photographic Prints; Studio Photography; Women
- Feridun Neset as a soldier. 13.6 x 8.6 cm, 18 May 1923; Sebah & Joaillier, Pera, Constantinople (Box 1, Folder 9)
  Albumen Prints; Boots; Constantinople; French Writing; Gloves; Hats; Individual Portraits; Istanbul, Turkey; Military / Soldiers; Ottoman Writing; Painted Backdrops; Photographic Prints; Studio Photography; Uniforms
- Soldier standing with a downcast gaze. İhtiyat Zabit Mektebi, Harbiye, Istanbul. 13.05 x 9.1 cm, 12 April 1912; Sebah & Joaillier, Pera, Constantinople (Box 1, Folder 9)
  Albumen Prints; Books; Boots; Constantinople; Furnishings; Hats; Individual Portraits; Istanbul, Turkey; Men; Military / Soldiers; Painted Backdrops; Photographic Prints; Studio Photography; Swords & Knives; Uniforms
- Group portrait with Velid Ebuzziya. 8.9 x 13.8 cm, Undated; Unknown (Box 1, Folder 9)
  Albumen Prints; Architecture; Bow Ties; Buildings; Canes & Walking Sticks; Eye Glasses & Sunglasses; Group Portraits; Istanbul, Turkey; Men; Photographic Prints; Streets
- Woman in black dress with black feathers. 13.1 x 8.1 cm, 9 September 1947; Studio Photo Abel, Constantinople (Box 1, Folder 9)
  Albumen Prints; Constantinople; Individual Portraits; Istanbul, Turkey; Jewellery; Photographic Prints; Studio Photography; Turkish Writing; Women
- Portrait of Mustafa Kemal. 13.9 x 9 cm, 1918; Studio Derounian Freres, Aleppo, Syria (Box 1, Folder 9)
  Albumen Prints; Aleppo, Syria; Hats; Individual Portraits; Men; Military / Soldiers; Mustaches; Mustafa Kemal Ataturk, 1881-1938; Painted Backdrops; Photographic Prints; Studio Photography; Uniforms
- Three men woth two shisha (hookah) pipes. 14.9 x 11.9 cm, Undated; Unknown (Box 1, Folder 9)
  Architecture; Coats; Constantinople; Fezes / Tarbouches; Furnishings; Gelatin Silver Prints; Hats; Istanbul, Turkey; Men; Mirrors; Mustaches; Nargiles; Photographic Prints; Smoking
- Woman wearing hat, leaning on pillows. Armenian writing on front. 16.5 x 10.5 cm, Undated; Unknown (Box 1, Folder 10)
  Albumen Prints; Armenian Writing; Constantinople; Furnishings; Hats; Individual Portraits; Istanbul, Turkey; Photographic Prints; Studio Photography; Women
- Armenian Patriarch Nerses Varjabedyan (1837-1884), sitting, wearing Armenian clerical vestments. Armenian writing on back. 16.1 x 10.7 cm, Undated; Unknown (Box 1, Folder 10)
  Albumen Prints; Beards; Constantinople; Furnishings; Individual Portraits; Istanbul, Turkey; Men; Photographic Prints; Religious Clothing; Studio Photography; Turkish Writing
- Two boys and one girl standing on a carpet, holding flowers. A souvenir from Mahmud Pertev Pasha. 16.7 x 10.9 cm, 18 March 1890; Unknown (Box 1, Folder 11)
  Albumen Prints; Boys; Carpets; Children; Constantinople; Family; Family Portraits; Fezes / Tarbouches; Flowers; Girls; Hats; Istanbul, Turkey; Ottoman Writing; Photographic Prints; Studio Photography
- Girl and a boy standing in white gowns with palm fronds at their feet. 16.5 x 10.8 cm, 1892; Abdullah Freres, Constantinople (Box 1, Folder 11)
  Albumen Prints; Boys; Children; Constantinople; Family; Family Portraits; Girls; Istanbul, Turkey; Painted Backdrops; Photographic Prints; Studio Photography
- Two girls and one boy standing on a carpet with a book on a table. 16.6 x 10.8 cm, Undated; Abdullah Freres, Constantinople (Box 1, Folder 11)
  Albumen Prints; Books; Boys; Carpets; Children; Constantinople; Family; Family Portraits; Furnishings; Girls; Istanbul, Turkey; Painted Backdrops; Photographic Prints; Studio Photography
- Kenan as a young boy in ornate dress. 16.5 x 10.8 cm, 1895; Abdullah Freres, Constantinople (Box 1, Folder 12)
  Albumen Prints; Bicycles; Books; Boys; Carpets; Children; Constantinople; Fezes / Tarbouches; Flowers; Furnishings; Hats; Individual Portraits; Istanbul, Turkey; Ottoman Writing; Painted Backdrops; Photographic Prints; Studio Photography; Turkish Writing
- Two girls, one holding a basket of flowers and the other holding a stuffed bird, and one boy sitting on a tricycle. 16.6 x 10.9 cm, Undated; Abdullah Freres, Constantinople (Box 1, Folder 12)
  Albumen Prints; Birds; Boys; Children; Constantinople; Family; Family Portraits; Flowers; Girls; Istanbul, Turkey; Painted Backdrops; Photographic Prints; Studio Photography; Tricycles
- Sarven and Iseda Dumentz as young girls, sitting in a rowboat. 19.8 x 15.3 cm, 20 June 1908; Sebah & Joaillier, Pera, Constantinople (Box 1, Folder Oversize)
  Albumen Prints; Boats; Children; Constantinople; Family; Family Portraits; French Writing; Girls; Istanbul, Turkey; Painted Backdrops; Photographic Prints; Studio Photography; Water
- Portrait of W.W. Peet, Esq. Writing, "Amerikan Bord Heyeti" stamp on back. 19.2 x 14.1 cm, 1900; Sebah & Joaillier, Pera, Constantinople (Box 1)
  Beards; Constantinople; Gelatin Silver Prints; Individual Portraits; Istanbul, Turkey; Men; Photographic Prints; Studio Photography; Turkish Writing
- Two girls in light colored gowns sitting on furniture. 16.2 x 10.6 cm, Undated; Studio Photo L'Aigle, Grand Rue de Pera 429, Constantinople (Box 1)
  Constantinople; Family; Family Portraits; Furnishings; Gelatin Silver Prints; Girls; Istanbul, Turkey; Painted Backdrops; Photographic Prints; Studio Photography
- Soldier with mustache in uniform and hat. 23.6 x 16.1 cm, Undated; Studio Photo L'Aigle, Grand Rue de Pera 429, Constantinople (Box 1)
  Constantinople; Gelatin Silver Prints; Hats; Individual Portraits; Istanbul, Turkey; Men; Mustaches; Photographic Prints; Studio Photography; Uniforms
- Two men in coats and hats, one man lighting his cigarette from the other's. 7.8 x 4.6 cm, Undated; Sebah & Joaillier, Pera, Constantinople (Box 1, Folder 13)
  Albumen Prints; Canes & Walking Sticks; Cigarettes; Constantinople; Gloves; Hats; Istanbul, Turkey; Men; Mustaches; Photographic Prints; Smoking; Studio Photography; Umbrellas
- Adele and Therese Honegger as young girls, in white gowns sitting on a chair. Therese Honegger also appears in ref8 and ref69. 10.5 x 6.3 cm, Circa 1868; Abdullah Freres, Constantinople (Box 1, Folder 13)
  Albumen Prints; Children; Constantinople; Family; Family Portraits; French Writing; Furnishings; Girls; Istanbul, Turkey; Photographic Prints; Studio Photography
- Arman Hisaryan as a boy standing, leaning against a table with a book in his hand. 10.6 x 6.5 cm, Undated; Abdullah Freres, Constantinople (Box 1, Folder 13)
  Albumen Prints; Books; Boots; Boys; Children; Constantinople; Furnishings; Individual Portraits; Istanbul, Turkey; Painted Backdrops; Photographic Prints; Studio Photography
- Man standing with walking stick. Armenian writing on front. 10.5 x 6.3 cm, Undated; Studio G. Wunsch, Vienna, Austria (Box 1, Folder 13)
  Albumen Prints; Austria; Beards; Canes & Walking Sticks; Carpets; Furnishings; Individual Portraits; Men; Mustaches; Photographic Prints; Studio Photography; Turkish Writing; Vienna, Austria
- Portrait of Crown Prince Mozaffar ad-Din (1853-1907), son of Naser al-Din Shah Qajar (1831-1896). English writing on back. 10.3 x 6.5 cm, Undated; Studio Window & Grove, London, England (Box 1, Folder 13)
  Albumen Prints; English Writing; Fezes / Tarbouches; Hats; Individual Portraits; London, England; Men; Photographic Prints; Studio Photography
- Portrait of Naser al-Din Shah Qajar (1831-1896) 10.3 x 6.5 cm, Undated; Studio Window & Grove, London, England (Box 1, Folder 13)
  Albumen Prints; Fezes / Tarbouches; Fur Garments; Hats; Individual Portraits; London, England; Men; Mustaches; Photographic Prints; Studio Photography
- Portrait of Ottoman General Omer Pasha (Michael Lattas, 1801-1871). 10.5 x 6.2 cm, Undated; Studio L. Angerer, Vienna, Austria (Box 1, Folder 14)
  Albumen Prints; Beards; English Writing; Fezes / Tarbouches; Furnishings; Hats; Individual Portraits; Men; Military / Soldiers; Mustaches; Photographic Prints; Studio Photography; Swords & Knives; Uniforms; Vienna, Austria
- Portrait of Muhammad III as-Sadiq (1813-1882), ruler of Tunisia from 1859-1881. Same subject as ref58. English writing on the back. 10.5 x 6.3 cm, Undated; Studio Disderi, Paris, France (Box 1, Folder 14)
  Albumen Prints; Beards; English Writing; Fezes / Tarbouches; Hats; Individual Portraits; Men; Mustaches; Paris, France; Photographic Prints; Studio Photography; Tunisia
- Standing portrait of Muhammad III as-Sadiq (1813-1882), leader of Tunisia from 1859-1881. Same subject as ref57. Writing on the back. 10.5 x 6.2 cm, Undated; Studio Disderi, Paris, France (Box 1, Folder 14)
  Albumen Prints; Fezes / Tarbouches; Furnishings; Hats; Individual Portraits; Men; Mustaches; Paris, France; Photographic Prints; Studio Photography; Tunisia
- Portrait of man with mustache. 10.7 x 6.6 cm, Undated; Studio Carlo Bukmedjian, Izmir, Turkey (Box 1, Folder 14)
  Albumen Prints; Individual Portraits; Izmir, Turkey; Men; Mustaches; Photographic Prints; Smyrna; Studio Photography
- Man with mustache and beard sitting on a chair. 10.3 x 6.1cm, Circa 1865; Abdullah Freres, Constantinople (Box 1, Folder 14)
  Albumen Prints; Beards; Constantinople; Furnishings; Individual Portraits; Istanbul, Turkey; Men; Mustaches; Painted Backdrops; Photographic Prints; Studio Photography
- Man with mustache sitting on chair, leaning on elbow on a table. 10 x 6.2 cm, Circa 1865; Abdullah Freres, Constantinople (Box 1, Folder 14)
  Albumen Prints; Carpets; Constantinople; Furnishings; Individual Portraits; Istanbul, Turkey; Men; Mustaches; Photographic Prints; Studio Photography
- Andon Hisaryan standing with a book in his hand, leaning on an upholstered chair. Name written on back in pencil. 10.6 x 6.5 cm, Undated; Abdullah Freres, Constantinople (Box 1, Folder 14)
  Books; Constantinople; Furnishings; Individual Portraits; Istanbul, Turkey; Men; Painted Backdrops; Photographic Prints; Studio Photography
- Woman in glasses, holding a white cloth, sitting next to a table with books. Identical to ref79. 11 x 6.7 cm, Undated; Studio Basile Kargopoulo, Constantinople (Box 1, Folder 15)
  Albumen Prints; Books; Constantinople; Eye Glasses & Sunglasses; Furnishings; Individual Portraits; Istanbul, Turkey; Painted Backdrops; Photographic Prints; Studio Photography; Women
- Seyyid Abdulkadir (1851-1925), Kurdish rebel leader. Ottoman writing, front and back. 10 x 6.3 cm, Undated; Abdullah Freres, Constantinople (Box 1, Folder 15)
  Albumen Prints; Beards; Books; Constantinople; Furnishings; Individual Portraits; Istanbul, Turkey; Men; Ottoman Writing; Photographic Prints; Studio Photography
- Sura-yi Devlet azasi (member of the state council) Muhsin Bey. 10.6 x 6.4 cm, 10 April 1888; Abdullah Freres, Constantinople (Box 1, Folder 15)
  Albumen Prints; Beards; Cairo, Egypt; Constantinople; Fezes / Tarbouches; Hats; Individual Portraits; Men; Ottoman Writing; Photographic Prints; Studio Photography; Turkish Writing
- Dr. Ali Haydar Bey (1880-1923). 10.4 x 6.1 cm, 1865; Abdullah Freres, Constantinople (Box 1, Folder 15)
  Albumen Prints; Beards; Constantinople; Doctors; Fezes / Tarbouches; Fur Garments; Hats; Individual Portraits; Istanbul, Turkey; Men; Ottoman Writing; Photographic Prints; Studio Photography; Turkish Writing; Umbrellas
- William Gottlieb Schanffler (August 22, 1798 – January 27, 1883), German missionary, and his wife Mary R. Schanffler (Reynolds). Names written on front. 10.4 x 6.3 cm, Circa 1868; Abdullah Freres, Constantinople (Box 1, Folder 15)
  Albumen Prints; Beards; Constantinople; Furnishings; Istanbul, Turkey; Men; Photographic Prints; Studio Photography; Women
- Vezir Mehmed Memduh Pasa (1839-1925), statesman, writer, poet. 10.5 x 6.3 cm, Undated; Abdullah Freres, Constantinople (Box 1, Folder 16)
  Albumen Prints; Books; Constantinople; Fezes / Tarbouches; Furnishings; Hats; Individual Portraits; Istanbul, Turkey; Ottoman Writing; Pens & Inkwells; Photographic Prints; Poetry; Studio Photography; Turkish Writing
- Therese Honegger as a young girl. Subject also in ref51 and ref8. 10.5 x 6.3 cm, 1869; Sebah, Pascal (Box 1, Folder 16)